A Guide to the Pay and Ration Claims of Virginia Veterans of the Spanish American War from the Virginia Office of the Governor, 1906-1913
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Pay and Ration Claims of Virginia Veterans of the Spanish American War from the Virginia Office of the Governor, 1906-1913
The Library of Virginia
24545
5 boxes
Virginia Office of the Governor
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 24545, Transferred October 17, 1956 from the Virginia Office of the Governor.
Biographical Information
On April 25, 1898, the United States declared war on Spain. Immediately, the Secretary of War telegraphed J. Hodge Tyler, the Governor of Virginia, stating that three regiments of twelve companies of infantry were required for the war effort. Virginians served in four volunteer regiments, the 2nd, 3rd, 4th, and 6th Virginia Regiments. The three regiments consisted of four companies from the 1st Regiment Infantry, eight companies from the 2nd Regiment Infantry, nine companies from the 3rd Regiment Infantry, eight companies from the 4th Regiment Infantry, two companies of the 3rd Battalion Infantry, and two companies of the 4th Battalion Infantry. With the addition of three new companies organized in Fairfax, Wytheville, and Lynchburg, these thirty-six companies comprised the three regiments which were designated the 2nd, 3rd, and 4th Virginia Infantry. Later, another regiment, designated the 6th Virginia Infantry, was created to fulfill the President's additional call for volunteers. The 1st and 2nd Battalions Infantry, consisting of colored soldiers, were mustered into this regiment.
Although the United States did not declare war against Spain until 25 April 1898, fourteen Virginia sailors were killed or listed as Missing in Action as a result of the explosion of the USS Mainein Havana Harbor on 15 February 1898. “Remember the Maine” became the battle cry for those Americans who held Spain responsible for deaths of American sailors. Two months later the war officially began. The Virginians who volunteered expected to see active service as a part of the Volunteer Army of the United States, but few of them ever reached Cuba. Of the four regiments, only the 4th Regiment was sent to Cuba, but they mustered out of service on April 27, 1899, so were only for a short time following the signing of the Treaty of Paris, which officially ended the war with Spain in August 1898. The 2nd Regiment mustered out of service in Richmond in December 1898, the 3rd Regiment mustered out in November 1898, and the 6th Regiment mustered out at Macon, Georgiea, in January 1899.
For a detailed account of the service of the Virginia Volunteers during the Spanish-American War, see the United Spanish War Veterans, Department of Virginia, Annual Report of the Department Historian (E714.3 U7).
Scope and Content
This collection of Spanish-American War records includes Pay and Ration Claim lists and vouchers and loose papers. An Act of Congress dated April 27, 1904, provided for reimbursing states for expenses incurred in raising and assembling state troops for the Volunteer Army of the United States. In the State of Virginia, this money was provided to the Governor to then be distributed to soldiers to cover pay and rations for the time served between April 28, 1898 (or from date enlisted, if later) and the date of muster in to service of the United States. Sol Cutchins of the law firm Cutchins and Cutchins was appointed at Disbursing Officer for these funds.
Claims for Commutation of Pay - Volunteer Soldiers for the Spanish War - Service to the State, undated, (rough draft) is arranged by Regiment, and by Company thereunder (includes muster in location). This volume is handwritten and includes columns for Name, Rank, Date when originally volunteerd, Date of enrollment, Date of muster in, Days of Service, Amount due, and remarks (number of years of service, rank changes, etc.). May also include information about soldiers discharge, transferred, died or deserted.
Claims for Commutation of Pay - Virginia Volunteer Infantry - Field and Staff Officers, undated, is arranged by Regiment, and by Company thereunder. The typed volume (2 copies) includes No., Name, Date of Enrollment, Date of muster in, Days of service, Rate per day, Amount due, Expenses (20 percent off), and Balance. Final page of each Company includes totals. See Claims for Commutation of Pay - Volunteers for the Spanish War - Service to the State for rough draft, which includes additional information.
Claims for Commutation of Rations - Spanish-American War, 1898, undated, is arranged Regiment of Virginia Volunteers, and by Company thereunder. This volume includes columns for No., Name, Time Allowed for (To and From dates), No. of days in service (at 75 cents per day), Amount allowed, Amount deducted from rations furnished, Balance allowed, Less 20 percent for cost of collection, and Balance Due Soldier. Each Company includes a total amount and the end of each Regiment includes a recapitulation. Includes 3 typed copies of this volume (one being a draft).
Loose Paper, 1925-1931, include bank statements, correspondence and interest cards. Bank statements, 1924-1938, include account balances. Correspondence, 1925-1931 includes correspondence between John Cutchins and various banks in the City of Richmond regarding the balance of undispersed funds deposited to pay Spanish-American War veteran claims. Also include one letter to Governor Trinkle regarding the same matter. Interest cards, 1925-1930, consist of monthly cards from banks indicating the amount of interest credited to the various funds established to pay Spanish-American War veteran claims.
Arrangement
Arranged in chronological order.
Contents List
- Second Regiment (Companies A-M), 1906-1913.
  - List of men issued pay checks, undated. (Box 1)
  - List of men issued ration checks, undated. (Box 1)
  - Voucher book of pay claims settled, 1906-1913. (Box 1)
  - Voucher book of ration claims settled, 1906-1913. (Box 1)
- Third Regiment (Companies A-M), 1906-1913.
  - List of men issued pay checks, undated. (Box 2)
  - List of men issued ration checks, undated. (Box 2)
  - Voucher book of pay claims settled, 1906-1913. (Box 2)
  - Voucher book of ration claims settled, 1906-1913. (Box 2)
- Fourth Regiment (Companies A-M), 1906-1913.
  - List of men issued pay checks, undated. (Box 3)
  - List of men issued ration checks, undated. (Box 3)
  - Voucher book of pay claims settled, 1906-1913. (Box 3)
  - Voucher book of ration claims settled, 1906-1913. (Box 3)
- Sixth Regiment (Companies A-M), 1906-1913.
  - Voucher book of pay claims settled, 1906-1913. (Box 4)
  - Voucher book of ration claims settled, 1906-1913. (Box 4)
- Second, Third, Forth and Sixth Regiments, 1906-1913.
  - Claims for Commutation of Pay - Volunteer Soldiers for the Spanish War - Service to the State (rough draft), undated. (Box 5)
  - Claims for Commutation of Rations - Spanish-American War, 1898 (three copies), undated. (Box 5)
  - Voucher book of pay claims settled, 1908. (Box 5)
- Loose papers, 1924-1938.
  - Bank statements, 1924-1938. (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1931. (Box 6)
  - Interest cards, 1925-1930. (Box 6)